<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Documentation on Sputter Documentation</title><link>/docs/</link><description>Recent content in Documentation on Sputter Documentation</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 02:17:43 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/docs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Introduction</title><link>/docs/introduction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 02:17:43 +1000</pubDate><guid>/docs/introduction/</guid><description>Sputter is a flexible and highly configurable API server to retrieve hard drive temperatures, and optionally publish them via MQTT.
In short, Sputter will gather up hard drive temperatures from a number of sources either on-demand or on a timer, and then return those temperatures while optionally also publishing those values over MQTT. Sputter also includes first-class support for Home Assistant so it can publish those temperatures as entities in Home Assistant.</description></item><item><title>Quickstart</title><link>/docs/quickstart/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 02:17:43 +1000</pubDate><guid>/docs/quickstart/</guid><description>Due to its flexibility and extensibility (and its complexity behind the scenes), there&amp;rsquo;s a few ways of getting started with Sputter. The first choice is which tool you want to use: the CLI or the Server.
CLI: Standalone command-line-only utility to gather drive temperatures from all the supported sources and outputs them to the console, optionally also publishing the measurements to an MQTT server. Server: Server application that runs a HTTP API that you can query to gather drive measurements and optionally publish those measurements to an MQTT server and/or to Home Assistant.</description></item><item><title>Command-Line/CLI</title><link>/docs/command-line/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 02:17:43 +1000</pubDate><guid>/docs/command-line/</guid><description>💡 The Sputter CLI supports both Windows and Linux! Just download the right binary for your target platform. Getting Help linkYou can use the -h/--help option to get help for the available commands and options when using the CLI:
USAGE: sputter.exe [filter] [OPTIONS] ARGUMENTS: [filter] OPTIONS: -h, --help Prints help information -v, --version Prints version information --scrutiny-api --mqtt-server --mqtt-credentials The default command will discover any local drives using the default adapters and gather measurements from all of them.</description></item><item><title>FAQ</title><link>/docs/faq/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 02:17:43 +1000</pubDate><guid>/docs/faq/</guid><description>This is just a random selection of questions that might not be answered elsewhere!
How do I update the Server configuration? linkIf you&amp;rsquo;re using the configuration file (i.e. sputter.json or appsettings.json), you can generally update the file in-place and the server will automatically reload the configuration. In particular, updating the MQTT broker details, auto measurement intervals, or drive filters will apply the changes without restarting the server.
That being said, if you weren&amp;rsquo;t already using the configuration file, or are using the server in limited environments, you might need to restart the server.</description></item></channel></rss>